this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello all welcome to software
engineering radio
this is your host kanchan shrinky our
guest today is casey alwith
casey is a principal at costanova
ventures an early stage we see firm
in today's episode we will explore
questions an entrepreneur may have
when starting to think about obtaining
vc funding
and what vc firms look for before
costanova
casey was a software engineer at
pinterest casey
is now focused on sourcing evaluating
and investing
in the next generation of enterprise
software companies
she has invested in companies like coyle
cyril
and stackhawk welcome casey really
looking forward to our conversation
today
same here thanks so much for having me
on kanchen before we start i'd like to
point listeners to three related
episodes
the first is 373 joel spalsky on
startups growth and valuation
episode 448 which is matt abbersfeld on
starting your own software company
and for the last one i don't have an
episode number yet but
it's a roland savage on getting a quiet
casey let's jump into it with a very
very basic question
what is venture capital and what is
private equity
sure so venture capital is a form of
and a type of financing that investors
provide to startup companies
and small businesses that are believed
to have very high growth potential
so they're similar in that they both
want to see
the value of the equity that they
purchase increase
over time but there are some pretty key
differences
with the types of companies that they
invest in so i'd say both in terms of
the company's life cycle
and how fast the business is growing
some pretty key differences with how
much capital they put to work
and then also with how much of the
company they'd likely own
after the transaction so i'm a venture
capitalist
i'm investing in early stage companies
and in some cases these are pre-product
two-person teams with no revenue and in
some cases they're a little bit further
along
as i mentioned we hope that these
companies are growing pretty quickly
and we'd hope to own about 20 of the
companies
so founders would very much be in
control of the board
and also own a majority of the company's
shares
in private equity or pe the companies
are
going to be much later staged
potentially not growing super fast
or distressed but they'll definitely
have significant revenue
and so a pe firm will come in and buy a
controlling stake of the company
and usually make pretty big changes to
it so
maybe replacing the management team or
sort of infamously
cutting lots of roles from the company
and by correcting these you know
quote unquote inefficiencies they hope
that the company will get back on track
and growing more quickly okay so my key
takeaway was
venture capital more early stage
private equity is probably at a much
later stage
but even with early stage you know can
you talk about
angel investors versus seed investors
and vcs you say you're an early stage vc
but how do you compare to angel and seed
investors
so there are a handful of differences
between angels and vcs
i'd say the big ones are where the
capitals coming from
when each one might invest in a
company's life cycle
probably the check sizes they're writing
and then
potentially some of the corporate
responsibilities
so angel investors are investing
personal capital into companies
whereas a venture capitalist vc is
investing institutional capital
on behalf of their limited partners so
think something like a university
endowment a large pension fund
or high net worth individuals
so to take an example maybe of a very
early stage security company that was
just founded
to get the initial product built the
founder might raise
a 200k friends and family round
and obviously include you know mom and
dad but also some other angel investors
as well who might be senior operators or
technical experts in the security space
and the check size is going to vary a
lot
it can be anywhere from you know single
digit thousands
up to maybe 100k so then
you know the security company with that
initial capital
begins to grow they start monetizing
and then they want to go out and raise a
two million dollar seed round
six months later and unless you have
very
rich friends you're going to have to go
and talk to a venture fund
that invests in seed companies so a vc
might offer
to invest a good portion of the round
you know let's say
1.8 million dollars of the 2 million
that remaining
200k of the allocation might go to
angels
or maybe another smaller fund but
they're going to be a much smaller
portion of the round
overall the vc will also probably go
and create a board seat with this round
of financing
so there will be some governance
component that emerges
out of the financing so angel is
personal
we see is institutional with other
related structure
that's right you talked about rich
friends what about crowdfunding
you know there's a lot of emergence of
crowdfunding today does that
can that take the place of rich friends
sadly we all can't have rich friends i'd
say
you know crowdfunding is very
interesting previously
companies were only able to raise
capital
from accredited investors so you know
that's what we're talking about with
rich friends
these high earning or wealthy
individuals that all started to change
in 2012 the jobs act passed
and this changed something called title
iii
which really enabled what we think of as
crowdfunding today
and title iii is also referred to as
regulation cf if you want to go and
learn more about it
but essentially what this did was allow
early-stage companies
to raise up to 5 million dollars from
any individual
so not just institutions or accredited
investors
so at a high level crowdsourcing is
generally good for the industry
it allows people who are not accredited
more fair access to private investment
opportunities
and as we all know there are a lot of
gains happening in the
early stage private markets so even
though
it is a risky asset class the
sec decided to not limit access to it
in my opinion i'd say crowdfunding isn't
right for every type of business
i think it's probably better suited for
consumer products
maybe a physical good where you can
spread the word via
the crowdfunding campaign and your
customers can become your
investors so to speak where it's not
great
is really for enterprise businesses
because you have to disclose
a ton of information to the public
and so if you're building an enterprise
software product and have
competitors that's probably not the most
advisable thing
okay so i think that sets the stage at
least for me
i can understand the difference between
angel and institutional
funding a little bit about crowdfunding
too i'd like to focus
for the next few minutes maybe several
minutes
thinking through the point of view of
someone who is maybe three or four years
out of grad school and has an idea
if i am that person how do i go about
executing my idea
should i raise money right away if not
how do i know when the time is right as
someone who may not know much about this
can you give us some advice can you give
me some advice
sure so raising venture capital
isn't right for every business because
once you raise
outside capital you have a level of
responsibility
to produce a return on that money so you
sort of have that extra layer of
accountability
and venture businesses in a lot of ways
are valued
off the growth rate of the business and
so if you don't think that
what you're building will be a high
growth opportunity or that's not
achievable
then it's probably not the best option
so there are plenty of things
you can do though before raising capital
of course you should be having
lots of conversations with potential
customers and
folks in the industry maybe validating
some wireframes you built to get early
product feedback
and you know depending on what your
specific skill set is possibly
co-founder dating
if you're looking for someone to really
balance out the skills of the founding
team
and so i'd say ahead of making that
decision of whether or not to raise vc
money
it's common for founders to bootstrap
with their own money
so to keep bootstrapping though you have
to have customers paying you
pretty quickly to remain a viable
business and
that's going to be hard to do if the
product is just built and maintained by
one person you'll probably need some
capital to go and
you know hire engineers or maybe someone
to service your
customers so one option
and i've seen this done in a handful of
companies but
some businesses might start out more in
a professional
services capacity solving a very
specific problem
and then sort of productize from there
and so that's one way i've seen
a handful of successful bootstrapped
businesses get off the ground
so it's sounds like it might be a good
day to bootstrap with your own money
when you start wanting to grow you want
to make the team larger
you explore we see funding
so i did that and i have a choice now i
have a few different investors
that i want to approach what should i
look for
you know what value can a vc bring to
the table other than capital
so when you pick your first early stage
investor
it is important to remember that this
person
could legitimately be on your board for
10 years
so it's definitely an important decision
and not something to go and rush into
so i think beyond capital i'd want to
know if i trust the person
do i respect their opinions do i think
we're capable of having
intellectually honest maybe even
challenging conversations
together and so for founders you know
i'd really reference the vc talk to
founders that they've worked with
where things you know went well but also
where things really
maybe didn't go well i think you can
learn a lot from those
conversations also as more capital has
come into the early stage markets in
recent years
it's definitely been forcing vcs to
redefine their value to remain
competitive in the market
and so early stage partners and firms
are becoming more specialized
in their investment sector focus areas
you know 10 15 years ago there were
plenty of generalist funds
and partners and now we see funds that
are highly specialized
at the early stages you know there's a
fund called heavy bit
for example which is focused on working
exclusively with developer tools
companies
and so firms are continuing to build out
these sort of value-added portfolio
programs to support
founders depending on what space they're
in as an example
costanoa has senior partners in sales
marketing and talent recruitment
and they do nothing but work full-time
with our early stage enterprise
portfolio
so it sounds like you know there is this
concept of
building trust and long term because you
are going to be working with the
investor for quite some time
and there are firms that are
specializing in areas as well
so you know i decided who i want to
approach
what should i be prepared with you did
hint at some of this in your
bootstrapping discussion
but you know we know of many companies
in the late 90s i got funding based on
the idea alone
what would your advice be for the
entrepreneur today
how far along this idea you know really
should be
in the implementation before approaching
ovc
so i'd say every interaction with an
investor
you know whether it's a formal pitch or
maybe just a friendly catch-up meeting
with someone you know
pretty well it's an opportunity really
to test your story
and so while fundraising and investor
relations are not
the most important part of building a
company it's still an incredibly
important
piece of it and can definitely give your
company a real advantage
over its competitors so more tactically
i think at a very minimum if you're just
starting to think about raising
and are having casual conversations with
the vc
i really recommend writing a one-pager
this
is not something you need to share
externally
but it'll just help kind of distill your
thinking on
how you're defining the problem and the
opportunity that you're tackling
you don't really need to have customers
or revenue but
you need to have done significant
customer discovery
i'd say if you're actively trying to
raise capital it is
definitely my strong preference to have
a deck and a plan
you know even if you don't have a
product yet and you haven't hired
really anyone else on the team i do like
to see the high level plan that includes
you know the hiring ramp
product milestones and sort of the
projected customer attraction
and to me you know the reason i love to
see it even if the company is really
early is it just shows that you're
thinking strategically and can kind of
tie those
basic business pieces and blocks
together which is
obviously an important trait and a
founder and ceo
so have a deck and a pager a one a deck
related to the business plan and a one
pager
on the idea you must have seen many of
these pitches
what makes a good pitch so i'd say all
good pitches come with
a ton of practice no matter how
experienced
the ceo is there are a few things that
founders can do
in a pitch that i really like personally
the first thing is
proactively addressing the risks in the
business instead of sort of hiding them
away
for example if your product or company
is very blatantly competing with another
large player in the market
but you never bring it up once in hours
of conversation
i just don't think that's very realistic
so i like to see those
be addressed proactively the second
thing
i like to see is having the founders
share what kind of key metrics they're
tracking internally
whether that's on the product side or on
the customer side
i really like the quote you make what
you measure and so
sharing the handful of those handful of
top level
company goals that you care about gives
me a better sense of
what's important in the business the
third thing i like to see is sharing
learning moments
i really like when founders talk about
how they've gotten
to where they are today and of course no
startup journey
is linear so having the humility to
share
mistakes and more on the experiments
you've run
paints a more realistic picture of what
it would actually be like to work
together
and then the last thing is you know less
about style but
of course it's always exciting to have a
recent burst of momentum
so maybe you've just closed a really
large enterprise contract
you've hired a key exact or you just
announced a product feature
but it's kind of nice to see those
tangible milestones as well
sounds good so share learning metrics
and of course you know a recent success
is awesome which certainly energizes
everyone
se radio listeners we want to hear from
you please visit
se-radio.net survey to share a little
information about your professional
interests and listening habits
it takes less than two minutes to help
us continue to make se radio even better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential
that's s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
so you know we had a good pitch we you
know we want to work together
now i understand there are multiple
phases of funding i've heard of a b
and c rounds can you talk about that
sure
so each round from seed to c
i'd say is underwriting a different kind
of risk
and each round as we see companies raise
more money
at higher valuations is really to
recognize
the continued growth and progress from
the last round
so most seed investors would say very
basically that they're
betting on the founding team and that
the market is a good one to play in
and i generally do agree with that i'd
say seed rounds today are
it's kind of a wide range but in between
one and five million dollars
usually falls somewhere in the middle at
series a
a company will have some revenue the
market right now
you know as we've sort of alluded to is
valuing companies ahead of traditional
benchmarks but when i think of what a
traditional
series a was like and maybe this was two
three years ago
the company would maybe have about a
million dollars in
annual recurring revenue you know
ideally added in the prior
12 months and the signs of kind of an
early
talented team and maybe some initial
signals that
they're getting ready to build out some
scalable processes on the sales and
marketing side
and a series a and this market is a
little bit bigger but it might be
between you know 8 and 15 million
dollars
when you go and raise the series b i'd
say the bet is really
on whether or not the company is ready
to scale
so the company will probably have
between
you know three and ten million dollars
in annual recurring revenue
and later stage investors will want to
put more capital to work
so they might be investing close to 30
million dollars in the round
and then series c investors come in and
they're usually betting on the continued
scale
and typically proof that the market is
big enough
for the company to continue to run so of
course those rounds are even larger than
the series b
and even higher valuations so how much
money
would i need and you know how long can i
keep getting funding before
my company really needs to be
self-sustaining or
you know i think you talked about series
b was up to
30 million so how much money you know
should an entrepreneur
typically have to raise right so we
typically recommend
that founders raise about two years of
capital with each round
if you want to raise a little bit more
and the terms are good
then it may make sense to raise a little
bit more capital and give your company
a bit of buffer i'd say on the specific
amount to raise
some products like an enterprise grade
security product
may just take a little bit more time to
build because of all the product
requirements that it may entail
so you know you might see a seed round
for that type of product closer to the
five million dollar
amount that i stated earlier but maybe
for a more
simple product that you can launch
quickly you might raise
you know one to two million dollars so
two years capital
with each round is there some advice
there with related to
also how much equity you need to give
away how do you balance
you know how much money you raise versus
how much equity you might have to
give away so i'd say the average
early stage round in aggregate has the
founding team taking
between you know 20 and 30 dilution on
the financing
if the team is more experienced or maybe
you've had some fast traction
you can get closer to that 20 dilution
mark
i'd say it's hard to take less dilution
than this because
most leading funds are going to be
ownership
centric and 20 is really seen as that
line that most major funds are trying to
get across in the early stages
so then by the time the company has gone
public
or you know has been taken over how much
of that equity is
you know gone or distributed i should
say
to maybe to the early stage employees or
to the investors
so the answer to that depends on how
much capital
the company is raised privately and also
what the terms were
on each round i'll also add two if you
have
multiple co-founders that will have a
pretty significant effect on how much
you might own as an individual by the
time your company goes public
i think it's most common for the
founders to own
between you know 10 and 20 percent of
the company at the time of the ipo
that can be one founder or it can be a
group of three or four co-founders
but again this can vary pretty
significantly
so i'll give an example when snapchat
went public
the two co-founders evan spiegel and
robert murphy
owned a combined 37 percent of the
company
on the other end when lyft went public
the two co-founders jointly owned about
six percent of the business together
and it's important to remember too ipos
are a dilutive financing event so
you are raising money and diluting
yourself in that process
i've heard about safe notes are they
different from giving up equally
so safes have become pretty popular in
early stage companies
safe stands for simple agreement for
future equity
and it's a type of financial instrument
that y combinator
popularized in the early 2010s
as you can tell from the expanded
definition it's an agreement for
future equity so it's actually neither
debt nor
equity safes in today's world when we
talk about them
are typically being referred to as post
money saves
which is actually a little bit different
from how they initially started
when they first came out founders like
safes because
they don't really have all these
governance components that
equity rounds have and so they really
keep the legal diligence and the legal
fees
and all of that to a minimum and so you
can close your round out
pretty quickly sometimes honestly in a
matter of days
and with the governance component as i
mentioned
there's not going to be an official
board created for the company
or anything like that so all in all
they are a very founder-friendly
instrument and
we're in a founder-friendly environment
so we do see a lot of them
at the early stages a slightly different
track now but
you know continuing on our journey as an
entrepreneur
how should i be thinking upon getting
all the return of
on my hard work do i really have to wait
until the ipo
or acquisition or is there payoff
as navigating through all the stages of
funding
so it is pretty challenging to get
significant liquidity or pay off
before an ipo or a good acquisition
you know the trade-off of course is a
smaller near-term salary for the
potentially
huge value of your equity over time
before an ipo or acquisition happens
though
there are a handful of ways that some
founders can see
pay off but they traditionally come with
hitting business milestones or
you know raising another financing round
so to start with executive compensation
does increase over time but it's usually
tied to company performance and
financings another thing
some founders can do is to sell a small
percentage of their holdings
usually at incremental rounds so
investors might allow a founder to sell
something
like up to 10 or 15 of their shares
at the series b or c and since it does
take
a longer time for companies to go public
these days
you know it's close to 10 years founders
may value having some cash today
to do something like buy a house or send
their kids to college for example
investors definitely do prefer that the
amount sold
to be a little less since we do want
that alignment with the founder and we
do want them invested
equity wise we do recognize though it
can be
pretty meaningful to founders to take a
little bit of capital off the table
with success before an ipo or an
acquisition though
so just summarizing our conversation
over the last several minutes
as an entrepreneur i should be careful
about the pitch
i would start with a seed round and the
goal would be typically to make sure i
have
about two years of funding as i move
through the bnc rounds
at the ipo stage or the as the company
progresses and
when i come to the ipo stage i would
expect that the co-founders typically
have
up to somewhere between 20 and 30
percent
of the equity in the company or could be
lesser as well
is that a fair summary yes i think
that's a fair summary
so that's it a couple more questions
here what
common mistakes would you see a
first-time entrepreneur make
that would make this journey not as
straightforward as
we have painted the picture here so i
have a few
that come to mind the first thing is not
picking the right co-founder
so if you have two co-founders you want
to make sure that that
atomic team can both sell and build
and i think one without the other is
going to put you
at a disadvantage and so you want to
make sure you bring on a balanced skill
set
when you're getting started there are
some exceptions but i'd say
for technical products i do like to see
that balance in the founding team
today's sponsor is spot by netapp the
cloud automation platform that makes it
easy to deliver continuously optimized
infrastructure at the lowest possible
cost
get the most out of your cloud
investments by automating cloud
infrastructure to ensure performance
reduce complexity and optimize costs
their machine learning and automation
scale to exactly meet application needs
using the most efficient mix of
instances and pricing models
eliminating the risks of
over-provisioning and cloud waste
leverage spot with all leading cloud
platform services and tools
check them out at spot.io se radio where
you can find more information
request a demo or even start a free
trial
[Music]
so the co-founder is important and then
expanding to the team
you mentioned on your website that early
stage investing
is really really about the team and the
people
what do you mean by that you know what
else do you look for in the people and
the teams
yeah i'd say all of my investments are
fundamentally a bet
on the founder or co-founders and i look
for a handful of key things
the first one is really the ability to
hire and recruit great talent
so this is always surprising to
first-time founders but they probably
spend
up to 50 of their time recruiting in the
first year so if you're spending that
much of your time
doing something hopefully it's you know
highly leveraged time
the second thing i like to see is really
this sense of
urgency and sort of an obsession with
the product
so again building a high-growth company
it's not for everyone and you do
pretty much have to be a little bit
crazy or obsessed to want to do it
so you know do you light up with
positive customer feedback
do you show up you know a week later
after our first meeting with
a ton of notes from all your customer
interviews or new wireframes
i love to see that passion and you know
level of excitement and commitment to
the problem
and then the third and final thing i say
is to really have a growth mindset so as
a seed stage company
you can't just say all right that's it i
think we
you know solved the problem here the
product
is usually a really narrow slice of
functionality
and once you start working with
customers you've started to earn the
right to actually
hear them give you real feedback and so
it's important to really keep your ear
to the ground
and listen to what they're saying and
then build the right next thing
so hearing not just what you want to
hear but
is a really important trait that i look
for in early stage leaders
thanks for that casey i think that rolls
into my next question and next
segment which is about working at a
startup
so if i am looking to join an early
stage company
as an engineer how do i decide if it's
worth it given that so many companies
don't actually make it
so some of the insights that you shared
about looking at the company from a vc
angle may apply here
but somebody that's looking for a job
may not have
all that kind of information so what
would you advise
that you know somebody that's looking
for a job at a early stage company
figure it out so the truth is you know
early stage companies
aren't for everyone and that's fine but
i do think that everyone can benefit
from trying it once
it's good to know what you want to get
out of the experience before
joining the company you know do you want
to become an engineering manager
do you want to work in a customer
customer-facing function
and get more hands-on experience with
customers
you know there are certain goals that
you can set up for yourself
so that you come out of the experience
having learned something new
the people that i know working at
startups typically
name i guess two things that really drew
them to the opportunity
the first thing you know is the team and
the second thing is usually
having an impact so startups are a
really high velocity learning
environment
and at a startup you know if you
need to build something or do something
it won't happen
if you don't do it at a big company
there might be
a dozen other people who can do your job
so
some people love that level of
responsibility and some people really
don't like it
i've also seen startups be a great
career accelerator
so especially if the startup is growing
quickly and on a good trajectory and
you're at that company early
you really have the trust of the
leadership team and so you can really
quickly grow into leadership roles
that otherwise might have taken three
times as long
climbing up the corporate ladder so to
speak at a much more established company
and then the final thing i'll say is if
you are potentially interested in
starting a company
but don't yet quite feel ready to do
that
being in a startup environment is
probably the next best thing
to prepare you for that so it's good to
test it out and see
if you enjoy that sort of environment
thanks casey i think a lot of that may
have come from your experience at
pinterest as well is that right yeah
that's right i worked at pinterest and
then i also worked at a seed stage
company
called urx that was a yc company back in
the day
and i think that working at a startup
early in your career is a great move
as an engineer it can be a really
awesome learning experience either way
because you're going to get to build
something usually from scratch
in general too i think early stage
technical hires tend to be
actually a little bit more senior in
their career and so if you're joining a
startup as a more junior engineer
you're gonna get to work really closely
with these
senior level ics and that doesn't always
happen at big companies
at big companies i'd say there are
really standard development processes
and it's rare to actually get to build
something from scratch
when you're in a startup you know every
developer in the early days
is a decision maker and your work really
has outsized effects
on you know how things grow over time
so what languages you pick the tooling
and standards that you set up
all of those are actually really
critical decisions
and so again if you're thinking about
working at a startup
definitely go in with an idea of what
you want to get out of it
but i think as an engineer it's great
because
you'll get to actually build things
right so put on multiple hats and
build so switch gears now and let's
talk about the vc firm itself
so you made the transition from a
software engineer to
we see so is working at a vc firm an
interesting and attractive career path
in itself from what you've seen so far
it is i'm obviously biased but i think
it's also one of the
only finance jobs where you can probably
wear a t-shirt to work
so that's pretty important i think you
know in seriousness there's no other job
where you have to be learning constantly
this much
and i definitely value that i think
besides
maybe starting your own company this
might come in second
for just how much constant education you
have to be doing
in addition you know the exposure you
get to really talented
founders executives and other industry
experts is unparalleled
and so that's you know a thing that you
can get addicted to pretty easily
from a macro perspective there is
definitely more value
growing in private companies today you
know anecdotally
a lot of investment bankers are trying
to move
into tech since they see this and the
lifestyle is better
so it feels like there is just so much
opportunity
at the early stages and as a vc
you're getting to work alongside and are
compensated alongside
a company's success so how was your
experience when making the transition
you know what did you have to learn what
did you have to maybe unlearn and how
did you acquire business acumen
so i think working at a startup i
actually did get a lot of exposure to
some of the business aspects
you know i had early exposure to our
customers
their feedback what the key metrics were
inside of the business
and so i think i learned a lot through
osmosis just being on such a small team
when it came to my role as an investor
you're right i did have to learn some of
those
business fundamentals but i do think
again they're learnable and something
you can
pick up on the job and quite frankly
in early stage investing today there
isn't
too much financial data it happens to be
quite theoretical or maybe
high level you know at series a that
starts to change
but at the end of the day you're looking
at a financial model
and really asking high-level questions
like what are the key
assumptions or risks here that we're
underwriting in the business
i'd also say when you invest in a
company and
see it grow over the course of a number
of years
you know over many board meetings over
regular meetings with the founders and
the key executives
that additional increase in complexity
feels really natural
and so again you get to learn a lot on
the job
and because i'm working with you know
almost up to 10 early stage companies
that means i get to learn things pretty
quickly so learning on the job is of
course helpful but
starting at an early stage company was
also helpful it sounds like
yes that's right i think the empathy
that i have
for early stage founders is someone who
has been inside a very early stage
business that piece of it i definitely
value
having but a lot i've just had to learn
on the job
how is a vc company structured it's
complex
but a vc firm typically has an operating
company
that's an llc or a limited liability
and this is the company that operates
our business you know pays the rent and
salaries
and other expenses for the capital that
we're actually investing into companies
you know that's coming out of a fund and
each fund is a unique limited
partnership
and so the capital for that limited
partnership is coming from
you know what we call lps or limited
partners
and so lps for us are things like
pension funds or university endowments
and i'll note that those lps do not have
investment discretion over the capital
it's actually the general partners
of the limited partnership that will
make the investment decisions
every fund is a unique limited
partnership
so every fund will have its own unique
cohort of
investment companies within it and
once a fund is fully deployed and the
next fund is raised
the investment team then starts
investing out of that next fund
which will have its own separate cohort
of companies
so my summary for that would be that as
you had mentioned very early on
the venture capital firm is an
institutional investor
so within the venture capital firm there
are multiple
funds that raise money and as each of
them
mature then they used to then further
invest in early stage
software companies yep that's right so
you've been at question noah now for
several years
so i'd like to ask you a little bit more
questions on how you are measured
so as an investor how are you measured
and
what do you plan for as you know you
know certain number of
investments would be a hit so how do you
measure that probability
and how do you make sure that you're
successful so
of course when we invest in a company
you know we want to believe that it has
a major major outcome at the end of it
i'd say though in early stage venture
you know looking at it from the fund
level realistically what ends up
happening
is unfortunately more than half of your
companies are going to fail
or not reach an outcome and this is of
course
you know an early stage venture i'm not
talking about much later stage companies
here
so i think it's fair to say and this is
a little bit of anecdata
but i'd say less than 10
of the companies in a portfolio are
going to go and produce the vast
majority
of returns so maybe 10 percent is
producing
90 plus percent of the returns of the
fund
on a more formal basis you know there
are a couple of metrics that we use
in the industry to measure performance
the most important one
is called dpi and that stands for
distribution to paid in
and basically it measures what you have
distributed back
in capital to your lps so if you have a
100 million dollar fund
you want to return let's say 400 million
dollars or more in capital back to your
investors
sc radio listeners we want to hear from
you please visit se
radio.net survey to share a little
information about your professional
interests and listening habits
it takes less than two minutes to help
us continue to make se radio even better
your responses to the survey are
completely confidential
that's s-e-radio.net survey
thanks for your support of the show we
look forward to hearing from you soon
[Music]
okay your process really is ensuring
that
you are investing such that you have a
certain percentage of return
for the folks that are actually
investing in the funds for the vc itself
yeah that's right what does a successful
exit look like
for an early stage investor in a company
so a successful exit for an early stage
investor will depend a good amount on
the size of the fund
and so you know it's not just about
getting a company to ipo
or a high priced acquisition what also
really matters
is how much ownership the
venture fund actually has in that
company so
typically you want material ownership
i'd say between
10 and 20 of the business you know the
more the better
to return a fund that is maybe a hundred
million dollars
you're going to need at least one
billion
or you know a multi-billion dollar
outcome to return that fund
where you own a material percentage of
the company
but if you're a 400 to 500 million
dollar
early stage fund you're definitely going
to need to have a couple
of multi-billion dollar outcomes to
produce good returns for your investors
okay so let's talk about your investment
philosophy when it comes to selecting
ideas
you know what is it about the idea of
technology that you look for
so i'd say you know team and founder
market fit
really do determine the bulk of why i
would invest in an early stage company
you know good ideas people see them they
end up getting copied
and you might have a head start of a
year or something like that
but ultimately it's just going to really
depend on your
ability to build and execute quickly
you know that being said there are
definitely a handful of things that i
look for
with an idea or a certain piece of
technology
and those probably fall into three
categories
you know the first thing is i'm looking
for a
scoped and defined end user value
i'd say especially with technical
products you know you can't
go in and say you're going to have this
problem in the future
as an organization you really have to
solve an individual's problem
today so that's a big one especially in
technical products for me
the second one is the adoption paradigm
and how much time it takes for an end
user to see value
so the way i ask about this typically is
i'll ask
what does your onboarding flow look like
and so i'm trying to get a sense if the
product is complex or simple
what it looks like when you deploy it
and this very basically tells me a
couple of things about
what the go to market motion might look
like for the business
in the early days and then i'd say the
last thing i look at and care about
especially again with technical products
is the ecosystem of tools and the
developer community
around it of course as we know
developers have things they fall in love
with and want to use
and usually you know that toolkit that
they're using
all those tools are compatible with each
other so you can't come in
and reinvent the wheel and have them
relearn everything
so i'd say typically the ecosystems
around these tools
especially if they're open source or
maybe language specific
aligning with those communities early on
is a pretty powerful thing
so i i definitely look for that in early
technical products that i'm backing
okay so fit within the ecosystem solve a
real immediate problem
and have you know simpler onboarding
those are the three takeaways i got
that's right i think developers can be
lazy sometimes and if you can't show a
developer something that
excites them within you know 15 minutes
to an hour
it's going to be pretty challenging to
get them to come back later
and try the product what key trends are
you bullish on
maybe right now so there are a couple of
key trends
going on in cloud data infrastructure
that i'm excited about
you know as we know there's a ton of
activity in the open source
ecosystem and i'm seeing a lot of
compatible tools emerging at every part
of the data stack
and what's great here is that you can
really pick the best in class tool for
your specific use case
and sort of stack them all up together
so
one area that's exciting at least i
think is exciting
is around projects that are helping to
bring data lakes
up to par with some of the benefits that
something like a
cloud data warehouse might provide so at
the data management level
i think there are a handful of emerging
projects
that are helping give data lakes some of
the core data management features
like change capture data encryption and
caching and ingestion a lot of these are
solved in a cloud data warehouse like a
snowflake or a big query
but haven't really been solved for data
lakes yet
so i think there's going to be some big
developments in that area
in the next few years the second trend
is around developer authorization
i'd say with the recent massive
acquisition of auth0 by octa
for 6.5 billion dollars which was
announced i think in march of this year
it's clear that developer authentication
is a solved problem i'd say that
authorization though
which is you know the act of specifying
access rights and privileges to
resources
it's still in the very early days you
know especially for application
developers
we're seeing a lot of pain points around
this specific problem and
i think there's potential for a pretty
big company to be built here
we'll put some links around what you
mentioned especially octa i think that
is relevant to our discussion today
thank you for that
as we start to wind down i'd like to ask
you on a lighter note
if you've seen this one does the series
silicon valley
represent the realistic experience of
fostada have you seen it
so of course i've seen it the show in my
opinion is way too real
what i do think it does a good job of is
showing that sort of roller coaster that
happens in early stage startups you know
richard it feels like is
always battling with someone whether
it's his investors
or the ceo of huli and usually
you know those relationships are not as
antagonistic or antagonistic at all but
i think the show does a good job of
showing that the startup journey is
definitely not
you know just a linear path i do think
the
personas are obviously pretty
exaggerated but
in some cases they can be pretty spot-on
and they
probably do illustrate your advice on
having a good co-founder
and a good initial team that's right
is there anything that we missed today
that you would like to cover
well i really enjoyed our conversation
thank you so much for having me on this
kanchen
and you know if anyone in your audience
is thinking about starting a company
or wants to work with one you know i'd
love to meet them
and if you're interested in that please
do feel free to reach out to me directly
the other thing i'll say is that it is a
great time
to start a company right now it's a very
founder-friendly environment and there's
just a ton of activity
and so you know if you're waiting for
that sign i'll say this is your side
especially if you have a solution for
authorization
exactly so how can people contact you
if they want to so i'm pretty accessible
the best way to get in touch
is via email i'm just casey
costanoavvc.com
i'm also active on twitter and so if you
want to shoot me a dm on twitter
that's another good way to get in touch
we'll put your twitter handle in the
show notes
great thank you thanks so much casey
this is awesome
i learned a lot i hope our listeners did
too
this is kanchan shrinky for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening